<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>OLS on James Uanhoro</title>
    <link>https://www.jamesuanhoro.com/tags/ols/</link>
    <description>Recent content in OLS on James Uanhoro</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2019 11:43:14 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.jamesuanhoro.com/tags/ols/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Problems with using odds ratios as effect sizes in binary logistic regression and alternative approaches</title>
      <link>https://www.jamesuanhoro.com/post/2019/11/25/problems-with-using-odds-ratios-as-effect-sizes-in-binary-logistic-regression-and-alternative-approaches/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2019 11:43:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.jamesuanhoro.com/post/2019/11/25/problems-with-using-odds-ratios-as-effect-sizes-in-binary-logistic-regression-and-alternative-approaches/</guid>
      <description>This is my first (first author) journal article. We started writing it in Summer 2018, with first submission by November 2018. So my thinking has changed somewhat since then. There is a non-pay-walled version below, but the version of record is available at the Journal of Experimental Education, http://www.tandfonline.com/10.1080/00220973.2019.1693328. The best part of the review process was communicating with the editor, Professor Brian French - he was very kind.
Here&amp;rsquo;s the PDF and GitHub repository with simulation and figure reproduction code in R (very little comments).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling the error variance to account for heteroskedasticity</title>
      <link>https://www.jamesuanhoro.com/post/2018/05/07/modeling-the-error-variance-to-account-for-heteroskedasticity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.jamesuanhoro.com/post/2018/05/07/modeling-the-error-variance-to-account-for-heteroskedasticity/</guid>
      <description>One of the assumptions that comes with applying OLS estimation for regression models in the social sciences is homoskedasticity, I prefer constant error variance (it also goes by spherical disturbances). It implies that there is no systematic pattern to the error variance, meaning the model is equally poor at all levels of prediction.
This assumption is important for OLS to be the best linear unbiased predictor (BLUE). Heteroskedasticity, the complement of homoskedasticity, does not bias OLS, however, it causes it to be inefficient, losing the &amp;ldquo;best&amp;rdquo; property in the BLUE.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
