<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>effect-size on James Uanhoro</title>
    <link>https://www.jamesuanhoro.com/tags/effect-size/</link>
    <description>Recent content in effect-size on James Uanhoro</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2019 01:43:14 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.jamesuanhoro.com/tags/effect-size/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Large scale RCTs in education suggest small effects; this is not surprising</title>
      <link>https://www.jamesuanhoro.com/post/2019/12/06/large-scale-rcts-in-education-suggest-small-effects-this-is-not-surprising/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2019 01:43:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.jamesuanhoro.com/post/2019/12/06/large-scale-rcts-in-education-suggest-small-effects-this-is-not-surprising/</guid>
      <description>A recent article in the Educational Researcher by Lortie-Forgues and Inglis (hereafter LFI)1 concluded that large-scale educational RCTs for academic achievement are &amp;ldquo;often uninformative&amp;rdquo;, and found this to be cause for concern. LFI&amp;rsquo;s work is transparent and easy to follow. They gathered study results from two funding sources (one in the UK, another in the US) over the course of 11 years. All the studies were large scale RCTs. They had 271 outcomes from the 141 studies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Problems with using odds ratios as effect sizes in binary logistic regression and alternative approaches</title>
      <link>https://www.jamesuanhoro.com/post/2019/11/25/problems-with-using-odds-ratios-as-effect-sizes-in-binary-logistic-regression-and-alternative-approaches/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2019 11:43:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.jamesuanhoro.com/post/2019/11/25/problems-with-using-odds-ratios-as-effect-sizes-in-binary-logistic-regression-and-alternative-approaches/</guid>
      <description>This is my first (first author) journal article. We started writing it in Summer 2018, with first submission by November 2018. So my thinking has changed somewhat since then. There is a non-pay-walled version below, but the version of record is available at the Journal of Experimental Education, http://www.tandfonline.com/10.1080/00220973.2019.1693328. The best part of the review process was communicating with the editor, Professor Brian French - he was very kind.
Here&amp;rsquo;s the PDF and GitHub repository with simulation and figure reproduction code in R (very little comments).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>