<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Fit indices on James Uanhoro</title>
    <link>https://www.jamesuanhoro.com/tags/fit-indices/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Fit indices on James Uanhoro</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.jamesuanhoro.com/tags/fit-indices/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A Chi-Square test of close fit in covariance-based SEM</title>
      <link>https://www.jamesuanhoro.com/post/2017/11/16/a-chi-square-test-of-close-fit-in-covariance-based-sem/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.jamesuanhoro.com/post/2017/11/16/a-chi-square-test-of-close-fit-in-covariance-based-sem/</guid>
      <description>TLDR: If you can assume close fit for the RMSEA, there is no reason why you cannot for a Chi-Square test in SEMs. The method to do this is relatively simple, and may cause SEM practitioners to reconsider the Chi-Square test.
 When assessing the fit of structural equation models, it is common for applied researchers to dismiss the $\chi^2$ test because it will almost always detect a statistically significant discrepancy between your model and the data, given a large enough sample size.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Misspecification and fit indices in covariance-based SEM</title>
      <link>https://www.jamesuanhoro.com/post/2017/10/28/misspecification-and-fit-indices-in-covariance-based-sem/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.jamesuanhoro.com/post/2017/10/28/misspecification-and-fit-indices-in-covariance-based-sem/</guid>
      <description>TLDR: If you have good measurement quality, conventional benchmarks for fit indices may lead to bad decisions. Additionally, global fit indices are not informative for investigating misspecification.
 I am working with one of my professors, Dr. Jessica Logan, on a checklist for the developmental progress of young children. We intend to take this down the IRT route (or ordinal logistic regression), but currently, this is all part of a factor analysis course project.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>